<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The children's petition, or, A modest remonstrance of that intolerable grievance our youth lie under in the accustomed severities of the school-discipline of this nation humbly presented to the consideration of the Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3869A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25344</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08939235</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08939235</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42002</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32841)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42002)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1279:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The children's petition, or, A modest remonstrance of that intolerable grievance our youth lie under in the accustomed severities of the school-discipline of this nation humbly presented to the consideration of the Parliament.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>70 [i.e. 68] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Chiswel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, Novemb. 10. 1669. Roger L'Estrange."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>School discipline --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Punishment --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42002:1"/>
            <p>THE Childrens Petition: OR, A Modeſt Remonſtrance of that intolerable grievance our Youth lie under, in the accuſtomed Severities of the School-diſcipline of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Humbly preſented to the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>Licenſed,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Novemb.</hi> 10, 1669.</date> 
                        <signed>Roger L'Eſtrange.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwel</hi> at the two Angels and Crown in <hi>Little-Brittain,</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:42002:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42002:2"/>
            <head>The Childrens Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition and Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the happy advantage of the excellent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this Nation, that when we lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any oppreſſion of general importance, we may have our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42002:3"/>recourſe to this Great Council for Advice and Relief; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any end more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſical to ſuch an Aſſembly, or any honour more deſirea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>We the Children of this Land, who look upon our ſelves as no ſmall part of the Nation, while there is ſcarce any Houſe or Family whereof we make not our ſhare; nor our intereſt inconſiderable, while the good of us, as to you whoſe we are, is of the neareſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment that can be; are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldned to this humble Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, not ſo much of your pity and tenderneſs, as Fathers, as of the ſcrutiny and holineſs of Cenſors, and a juſt indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42002:3"/>and redreſs of that evil, which ſhall appear to you, upon mature conſultation.</p>
            <p>There is not any thing hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of more moment in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, then the Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Children, and yet is there generally nothing left more at randon, and beſides the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick care. It is the cuſtom or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily of our Schools, which being received from our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, and uſed upon our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent years (that are not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible either of our Maſters vice, or our own injury) does paſſe uncontrouled, to commit to a perſon who hath got a little Greek and Latin, and nothing elſe perhaps to live upon, and ſo is choſen to the Office (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42002:4"/>any qualification otherwiſe many times, either of real <hi>worth</hi> or virtuous <hi>life,</hi> it is well if it be but ſo much as of ſobriety in age, and modeſt inclinations) the liberty to uſe ſuch a kind of diſcipline over us, as that the ſpring-time of humane life, which in all other Creatures is left at the greateſt freedom to be ſweet and jocund, is deflou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and conſumed with bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and terror, to the drying up the very ſap which ſhould nouriſh our Bodies, and thoſe more lively ſpirits which ſhould animate our minds in our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture life, unto brave Actions.</p>
            <p>And if it were only the evil of our ſuffering we had to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of, ſeeing our unadvertent
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42002:4"/>Parents do give us up to this Carnage, we ſhould bear it: But when our ſufferings are of that nature as makes our Schools to be not meerly hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Correction, but of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, in this vile way of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation in uſe, wherein our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret parts, which are by nature ſhameful, and not to be unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, muſt be the Anvil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the immodeſt eyes, and filthy blows of the ſmiter; We are confounded with the horror, and could wiſh we had ſome ſuch way, as by turning up the ſoal of our Shoe, (which they uſe, they ſay, among the <hi>Turks)</hi> to preſent to you our Grievance. For we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, if modeſty will ſuffer
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42002:5"/>the thing to be debated, it will be found certainly, to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, a matter to be adjudged amongſt the Apoſtles <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and thoſe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vvhich are not to be named. <hi>Ubi ſunt pueri qui ingreſſi ſunt? Fac ut prodeant, ut cognoſcamus eos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed one would think that this kind of puniſhment ſhould have been firſt invented on purpoſe, that an averſation to it, as an ugly ſordid and abhorrent thing, ſhould deter ingenuous perſons from inflicting it, ſo that nothing leſs then ſome very grievous crime ſhould ever wring a ſtripe from them; but when our contrary experience
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42002:5"/>does tell us how every light oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion is taken, with what ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite they come to it, as ſoon as the fleſh is bare, theſe Jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falcons are perching over us, their letting ſo few faults e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, and attending our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruing, for the moſt part, no longer then till they obtain this end, we are convinced vvith the ſad and inſufferable reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the invention hath been fetched originally, not from the Cloſet of <hi>Mercury</hi> or <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> but from the more powerful <hi>Goddeſs</hi> of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a certain trick of hers, to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leviate the pains and killing <hi>Crambee's;</hi> the Maſter other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe could never perhaps en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, if beyond the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42002:6"/>he hath in moſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from the Founder, he had not this ſly allowance under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand from her withal, as Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factrix to that function.</p>
            <p>It is diſputed againſt the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> vvho condemn all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that ſome paſſion is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the chaſtizement of Youth; and ſo is <hi>Ira</hi> defined by <hi>Lactantius, Motus animi ad coercenda peccata inſurgentis.</hi> A definition indeed very fitting the profeſſion of that Father, vvhoſe Latin doubtleſly is ſmoother then his ſpirit througout his Works. <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> in his Tract about <hi>Cohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Anger,</hi> hath laid down a Rule of a contrary impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, vvith excellent delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42002:6"/>which is to this ſenſe, <hi>That puniſhment ſhould never be inflicted out of ſelf-pleaſing;</hi> and conſequently from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, of that of <hi>Archytas, Vapulares niſi iratus eſſem,</hi> and others, when a man is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent enraged, he is firſt to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his own paſſion, before he is fit to puniſh the fault of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther under his intuition. To this ſame effect, <hi>Qui eſurit is cibo utitur ſecundum naturam, qui punit is nulla ad hoc impelli debet cupiditate,</hi> ſayes <hi>Seneca.</hi> Thoſe that adminiſter puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (ſayes <hi>Cicero</hi>) are to be <hi>Legum ſimiles, quae ad punien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum non iracundia, ſed aequitate ducuntur.</hi> That is, He that is hungry, uſeth his meat accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42002:7"/>to Nature, but he that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes, ought to be like the Laws themſelves, that are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to it with no ſort of deſire at all. <hi>Plutarch</hi> indeed ſpeaks cleanly, imagining nothing but of the pleaſure of revenge, and ſatiating ones anger; But what would he ſay of that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment which is made to ſerve a viler affection? <hi>Et de virtute locuti, Clunem agitant,</hi> as <hi>Juvenal</hi> has it.</p>
            <p>If puniſhment come from ſelf-pleaſing, Then will it not be in meaſure; Then will it not be juſt; Then the puniſher will be glad of a fault; Then will it be remedileſs to the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer, ſeeing the cauſe of the puniſhment lies in the puniſher,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42002:7"/>and not in the puniſhed to help it; Then every little occaſion, or none at all, ſhall be enough for the inflicter to give himſelf pleaſure. And then ſhall the innocent, who are little ones, and not able to conceive of this, be intollerably miſerable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought many times almoſt to their wits end, and ready to make away themſelves, rather then endure the iteration of thoſe torments, whereof they can ſee no reaſon, and wherein they can hope no end; having ſome cognation in this to thoſe of Hell, that they ariſe from an unquenchable fire, in the appetite of the Maſter.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Philip Sidney,</hi> that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Perſon, in his <hi>Arcadia,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42002:8"/>hath thought good to ſet forth this evil to publick view, and ſo to animadverſion, we may ſuppoſe and emendation, under the perſon of <hi>Cecropia,</hi> dealing thus with her Neices. <hi>Cecro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>imploying her time in uſing the ſame cruelty on</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mela, (as on <hi>Philoclea) her heart grew not onely to deſire the fruit of puniſhing, but even to delight in puniſhing them.</hi> This very ingenuous Gentleman had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, belike, this growing hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour in thoſe that uſe it; but having a Soul in which ſo foul a thought never entred, as might direct him right into the cauſe of it, he expreſſes the practice, complaining tragical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the cruelty, but ſearches
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42002:8"/>not to that rottenneſs which lies farther at the core of it. Will you hear that ſhrewd Author of <hi>Hudibras</hi> make the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very?</p>
            <q>
               <l>The Pedant in the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyes breeches,</l>
               <l>Does claw and curry his own itches.</l>
            </q>
            <p>By this little, we need not wonder if the Tyrant of old, who being expulſed his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, got to be Maſter of a School, ſhould chuſe that, for the more voluptuous domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Nor that any preſent Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies of the function in our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhould not, when time
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42002:9"/>ſerved, be won, to change this province, for any other, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to them, by the higheſt bounty.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Fronti nulla fides. Quis enim non vicus abundat</l>
               <l>Triſtibus obſcaenis? Caſtigas tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia, cum ſis</l>
               <l>Inter Socraticos notiſſima foſſa Cynoedos.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And indeed if there were not ſome ſuch thing, and that this at the root, how ſhould we meet ſtill with ſuch doings as we do almoſt in all Schools? How could men, who have the face of gravity and diſcretion, be ſo highly, and ſo readily of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42002:9"/>at all turns with inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Children, as they make themſelves to be? What think you? when a Boy ſhall be hoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed perhaps at firſt for the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a word, and then be held on in the asking more queſtions (which fear alone ſhall diſable him preſently to anſwer) until he receive ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtripes, or ſo grievous ones, if fewer, as the Rogue who is whipt for petty-larceny, comes off very gently many times in compariſon of this Lad; Who can think, if the puniſhment were not ſuffer'd to be on thoſe parts, that it were like to be ſo much? The blood which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed any where elſe, could
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42002:10"/>not but make the bowels yearn, and the hands relent, when the Child is ſo little, and the fault leſs. The blows could neither be ſo frequent or ſo ſore, if compaſſion were not choaked with ſomething elſe. For this is the miſery and plague above all, that when thoſe appetites, which are natural, have their end, and receive a completion and redreſs in the attaining of that end, the appetite which is unnatural, is infinite, and it is a thing the thoughts whereof is intollerable to us, that our ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and ſmart muſt encreaſe according to the ebb and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe deſires, which have no current this way in nature
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42002:10"/>to ſatisfaction &amp; a ſurceaſe. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if there be need for us to be ſtricken, for the eaſe and impatience of the Maſter, without any profit to us, let them not be the blows of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated villany, but of his preſent wrath, ſuch as a blow upon the ſhoulders, or a flirt on the ear ſometimes may be; we ſhall acknowledge it but a part of due humility, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to bear with him, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of his bearing ſo much with us: But if there be ſome other incentive to our beating, more inſatiable then that of anger in the caſe, we cannot but think it high time that the matter be look'd into
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42002:11"/>a little better then hath been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, whether indeed it be any longer to be endured in the Nation. We ſhall be ſorry heartily, if no reward but this can be ſufficient to hold the Able to this imployment, yet muſt not any be ſo gratified, nor Learning it ſelf be rated at the price of what is wicked. <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluti eſt hominis</hi> (ſayes one of the Fathers) <hi>in rebus ſeriis, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptatem quaerere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not unknown how the Jeſuites govern: their Schools beyond the Seas, nor what they have delivered ſome of them on this matter in their caſes of Conſcience; Neither would it be any diſhonour to us to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42002:11"/>change our cuſtoms for the better, though we borrowed them of other Countries. It cannot therefore but be a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to us that ever we ſhould have Parliaments in <hi>England,</hi> wherein are ſo many Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of excellent parts, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous reflections, and who ſome of them are not ſo old as to forget what was unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and yet we never hear of ſomething tendred for the regulation of Schools, and what is practiſed there. Is it becauſe you can indeed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member no ſtories? Or, that the impreſſions do yet laſt, that you muſt not tell tales from thence? And why muſt we tell
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42002:12"/>no tales of our Maſter or Dame? If there were no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciouſneſs of what is ugly in the fact, what need of this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy? Why is the Boy or Girl retired from their fellows, and why ſo long a preachment then made over the Bare in a Corner? The end of vertuous puniſhment is for example, and ſuch ſymptoms as theſe do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us, who indeed do moſt need to be amended, the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher or the Puniſhed, the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed or the puniſhment it ſelf, which will be found the greateſt delinquent. It may be ſaid, There is a neceſſity of ſome caſtigation ſometimes upon ſome occaſion, and this is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42002:12"/>moſt ſafe, or leaſt dangerous, that Children receive no hurt by it, and therefore is choſen and uſed. But this is but one thing well conſidered, and thoſe that look but on one thing in their deliberation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what is to be done, are eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſled into a wrong or ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low determination. There is more then this one thing in ſo momentous a matter, as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Youth, to come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſideration. You may eaſily provide for our ſecurity, that no bones be broken, and yet without the neglect of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and virtue.</p>
            <p>In truth, it is a Queſtion ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worthy the moſt mature
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42002:13"/>deliberation, whether Children ſhould ever be beaten at all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their Books. That cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtizement is fit for this Age up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on deſert, we denie not, and the holy Scripture aſſerts: But as that is a chaſtizement which is meet, ſo is it we ſuppoſe to be for ſin, or ſome moral fault. The underſtanding will never be inlightned, the memory healed, or the invention quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſtripes upon the fleſh. There are many dull'd, we are ſure; many diſcouraged, and ſome that have been undon by this means. <hi>Quintilian,</hi> that moſt famous Inſtitutor of Youth, though he would have Lads brought up hard, to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42002:13"/>able to endure any thing, as the lying on boards, eating the courſeſt fare, and the like, yet is herein expreſs; <hi>Coedi vero diſcentes quamquam receptum ſit, &amp; Chryſippus non improbet mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè vellem.</hi> But by no means <hi>(ſayes he)</hi> would I have thoſe that learn, to be beaten, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it is ſo commonly uſed. There are theſe Reaſons he renders; In the firſt place, It is a ſervile thing that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes only ſlaves or bruits, and ſo unworthy of any that are free-born, and much leſs ſuch who are the Sons of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Nobles. Beſides that, if you change the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Age, for the moſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42002:14"/>part it is moſt manifeſt injury and wrong. In the next place, If there be any whoſe diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo illiberal, as that it will not be amended by reproof and ingenuous notices, it is to be expected it ſhould become but the worſe for blows, and grow the more obdurate. In the third place, There will be no need of caſtigation, if the Maſter be ſo diligent as he ought, to ſee the task which he ſets to be done, by his own ſedulity and inſpection. <hi>Nunc ferè negligentia paedagogorum ſic emendari videtur, ut pueri non facere quae recta ſunt cogantur, ſed cur non fecerint puniantur.</hi> That is, The matter now a-days
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42002:14"/>is ordinarily ſo carried, the Boy is beaten to make amends for his Maſters careleſneſs and ſloth. Add unto this, that there is many times a hared brain, a ſtammering tongue, or the like very grievous ill habit or geſture introduced through terror; or there may be, at leaſt, according to this ſame Author, ſome deformed paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or uncouth words, which do fall from, or happen to thoſe that are beating, which leave ſuch impreſſions of ſhame and ſurprize on the more ingenuous and baſhful, that no advantage which can be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by any Maſter, is able to recompence the miſchief al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42002:15"/>ſuffered, if it be onely in the debaſing the Spirit, and rendring themſelves vile in their own imaginations. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, in the laſt place, he has theſe words; <hi>Jam ſi minor in deligendis cuſtodum &amp; Praecepto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum moribus fuit cura, pudet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere in quae probra nefandi ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines iſto coedendi jure abutan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Non morabar in parte hac, nimium eſt quod intelligitur.</hi> We will not Engliſh this laſt of his Reaſons, becauſe it is the very fore upon which we touch, and the riſe of this Addreſs; onely thus far, <hi>It is too much already</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>which is underſtood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The habitation of the <hi>Muſes</hi> are fancied by the Poets to be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42002:15"/>
               <hi>Amoena Loca,</hi> pleaſant Groves, delightful Hills, chryſtal Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, where Joy, and Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the Graces dwell. And what is it theſe ſignifie? Hath their <hi>Pernaſſus,</hi> and ſuch fictions, no meaning? Is it the ſteep toyl onely Learning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires in thoſe that will climb to it, or the refreſhing proſpect they intend by it to intice us up? What is it the Antients here would repreſent? Are their high Hills nothing indeed but Difficulty, and their Groves Birch? Is <hi>Helicon</hi> the Boys Tears, and <hi>Pegaſus</hi> the blind Horſe? Alas, that when we ſhould be invited to Learning, as to a Banquet, a pleaſant
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42002:16"/>Feaſt, and the deſire of our Souls, it is preſented to us ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver but in torment and dread! Alas, that the <hi>Muſes</hi> ſhould be put thus in the ſhape of <hi>Erinnis,</hi> and <hi>Thalia's</hi> Lute-ſtrings be made to yeeld no Sounds but Screeches and Cries? That when we go to School, we ſhould be driving to the Sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; when we go to our Books, we ſhould be carrying unto paines. <hi>Et ubi tor quentur, jam non membra, ſed vulnera,</hi> in <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prians</hi> expreſſion. Alas! how wide muſt the World needs be here, to think that Children, in their tender Nature, ſhould be made to love that (and who would not have Children love
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42002:16"/>their Books?) which is never offered them but with hate? You ſhould imbitter to us our pleaſure, and our ſin that will do us hurt; but you ſhould ſugar to us our learning, which is for our good. The Nurſe ſhould never put Wormwood on that Breſt from which ſhe would not have the Child to be weaned. We read of <hi>Marcus Portius,</hi> in the <hi>Roman</hi> Story, who eſtabliſhed a Law, That no <hi>Roman</hi> Citizen ſhould be beaten by the Magiſtrate with Rods. He ſhould be a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune of the People by our Vote, that could prefer a <hi>Lex Porcia</hi> in our Schools, and ſome Work-houſes, where poor
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42002:17"/>Children are imployed, in this Nation. If <hi>Solomon</hi> will have the Boys beaten, and the Maids beaten, let it be with a Wand, or ſuch a way as becomes the Vertuous, as well as the Severe. If <hi>Solomon</hi> will name a Rod too, it is a Rod for the Back: Let it be a chaſt ſtripping; but what need is there for making the Child good, to have the Maſter made naught? <hi>Solomons</hi> Corrections are ſpoken to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, which he adviſes too to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Children for their faults, and not Maſters for their Books; <hi>Furthermore we have bad Parents</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>that have chaſtned us after their own pleaſure;</hi> ſignifying, that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42002:17"/>we are yet to be in ſubjection as to them; but if we have Maſters that do ſo, it is a thing to be abhorred, ſeeing God does not, and the Good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently ſhould not, correct any but only, for their <hi>profit.</hi> Eſpecially ſeeing moreover, <hi>Quod aetatem infirmam &amp; inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae obnoxiam</hi> (as the aforeſaid <hi>Quintilian</hi> farther has it) <hi>nemini debet nimium licere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a thing here orderly worth the enquiry, what that power the Maſter hath over his Scholars is, and whence he hath it? All power we muſt know is either natural, or derived. The power of the Maſter is not of Nature; For what hath
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42002:18"/>one man of himſelf to do with the Child of another? The power which is derived, is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Supream, or Subordinate. The Supream Authority, is that which lies in the chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, whether it be derived to him immediately from God, as in this ſtate; or by conſent of the people, as in ſome others. The Subordinate Power, is that which is derived from the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream to the inferior Officers, who act in his Name, and from his Authority. The power of the Maſter now is no ſuch power neither, deriving from the Magiſtrate, or the Laws of the Nation; for he acts not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Boyes in the Kings
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42002:18"/>Name, as the Juſtice and the Conſtable, and the like Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers do. What then is this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventitious ſtrange power? Why, this power the Maſter hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Scholar, is that right of ruling him, which is given him by the Father. It is no power therefore Supream, but Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate; and not natural, but derived from that which is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural; and conſequently is no other, nor no more, or to any other purpoſe, then what the Parents do allow him. If a Father therefore ſhall commit his Child to a School for Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but ſhall not give the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter leave to ſtrike him, or if he does, yet not uſe this ſort of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42002:19"/>coercion upon him for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons mentioned, The Maſter cannot ſerve any ſuch Child in this ſaid faſhion, but he is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt; not to ſay alſo what is worſe, becauſe he uſurps an authority, he hath not commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, and ſo is accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble both before God and Man for ſuch an action. Let not him that is unjuſt be unjuſt ſtill; let not him that is filthy, be ſtill filthy.</p>
            <p>Not that we intend by this, to diminiſh the leaſt tittle of that reverence which is due to our Maſters. For when we derive their Authority from this Fountain, we do think it a part of the piety we owe to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42002:19"/>God and our Parents, to render honour to their Perſons, and obedience to their Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Dii Majorum umbris, tenuem &amp; ſine pondere terram,</l>
               <l>Spiranteſque crocos, &amp; in urna perpetuum ver,</l>
               <l>Qui praeceptorem ſancti voluere parantis</l>
               <l>Eſſe loco. —</l>
            </q>
            <p>It is our Parents, we know, from whom we derive our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the World; and it is our Maſters many times to whom we owe our more happy being, in regard of that ſhape and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion vvherein they caſt us for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42002:20"/>the ſerving our Generation, or living more to purpoſe in it. There is not therefore any ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration or gratitude we can pay them, nor any gifts or gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuities according to their abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from our Friends, no nor any Revenues that have been beſtowed on ſome Schools by the pious Erectors of them, vvhich vve think too much for the care and labour of any ſuch men vvho are but a little faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in this charge. We humbly think it vvere good that the ſtipends and emoluments of Maſters vvere augmented. But there is a certain payment vvhich they give, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; a ſalacious pay of theirs,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42002:20"/>which they take of us, and not from us, vvhereof vve crave an abatement; and about vvhich, as neither vvorthy nor: inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, or at leaſt vvhether it be ſo or no, according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſage of it, vve are vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to come to ſome account or argument vvith them.</p>
            <p>One Boy hath happily a good underſtanding and no memory; Another hath a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy memory and no judgment; A third hath neither memory nor judgment. The Boy vvhoſe memory is quick, looks over his Leſſon once or twice, and goes to play; the other tvvo ply their Book as hard as they can, and are not able to get it. The
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42002:21"/>Maſter comes now and puts the Boy who follows his play, to ſay his Part, he ſayes it, and ſo paſſes: The other two cannot ſay for their lives, and are bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Here is Nature in theſe Lads, and no fault puniſhed. If the Boy who has the memory, had been put on ſome other task requiring pains and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he ſhould have ſuffered, and one of the other eſcaped. Thus Fortune, not deſert, is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged or reproved. And what if the Maſter, who knows the difference of their abilities, ſhall purpoſely ſet each of them to ſuch tasks, unto which he knows their parts moſt defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive; how eaſie is it for him,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42002:21"/>as often as he is willing, to ſerve himſelf of any of them? Let us yet preſs this a little farther, It is the cuſtom of ſome Schools, or rather of ſome Maſters, to ſet their Boys a Law, That if we miſs ſuch a number of words, as ſuppoſe juſt three words, we muſt be certain of what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows: And herein muſt they appear very righteous men to us, that they impartially exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute their own rule, and none be ſpared. Now what unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable dealings are theſe with us? For one Boy to anſwer but three words in the whole, and miſs all the reſt, is more then for another to anſwer all the reſt, and miſs but three words.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42002:22"/>What is it whether a Boy miſs three words, or thirteen? It is his care or negligence, his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence or diſobedience is to be regarded. It is the Will and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour which alone renders him culpable or blameleſs. And what ſhall we judge then of ſuch School Edicts as theſe, but that either the Maſter is one that follows others in his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods without diſcretion, or that theſe Rules of ſuch who do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, or execute the ſame, are but fine Devices to give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves opportunity under the pretence of juſtice, (which will go among the Boys) to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie thoſe inclinations, which the tribe of theſe men, for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42002:22"/>ought we ſee generally, (if they be ſtill ſuffered) are ſure to catch (as faſt as we Boys that come but together, do <hi>our</hi> itch) of one another.</p>
            <q>Uvaque conſpecta livorem ducit ab Uva.</q>
            <p>There are no perſons of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent apprehenſions, who ſee a <hi>Maſter</hi> taken with their <hi>Child,</hi> as more pretty, ſprack, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous then others, can but be apt to think, that ſure this Maſter who ſo likes that Child, will be Ioth to beat him. But when we that come to School together, ſhall ſee this Lad ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out by his Maſter, and have
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42002:23"/>about half a dozen, or half a ſcore laſhes given him, by authority of that ſentence, <hi>Non caſtigo to quod odio habeam, ſed quod amem,</hi> rung in his ear, with repetition of the <hi>Quod amem,</hi> at every laſh; What ſhall we think of ſuch liking? When theſe laſhes farther ſhall be with a Weapon of that length and ſharpneſs, as when the Boy is ſet down, he is made ſo raw, that he is not able to ſit, what ſhall we think of theſe <hi>Quod a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mem's,</hi> in the Laſhers Mouth? And what then if the reaſon be enquired for this, there be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing found, but only a Head perhaps uncomb'd, a Band not put on aright, a word or two
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42002:23"/>miſſing in his Part, a pair of Stockings down at knees, or a Shooe that hath taken dirt. Certainly if this be the effect of the Maſters greater affection, how well were it for any of the reſt (ſo long as it would but make him thereby, not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to meddle with them) to be rather the Objects of his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deteſtation and hate? Here is a love towards Children, like that indeed of a Canibal to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward humane fleſh. Here are Butchers, unto whom our Parents ſhould ſend their Calves to be flead, rather then Maſters, unto whom they ſhould ſend their Children to be inſtructed, and corrected
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42002:24"/>with moderation. It may be perhaps a lighter matter in ſome others of this Robe, who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times have taken up a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of us, as we do Poynts, by the dozen, onely to make themſelves merry, to divert their thoughts, or catch them a heat; and ſo long as they do it but gently and indifferently, and with innocence otherwiſe, we may be apt to think little of it, when there is a difference to be made as to the affection and execution of what kind it comes. It may be only of laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or of wrath, or of ſomething elſe. For what is that concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence in humane nature, which is depraved and foul? What
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42002:24"/>that vile thing (if we may call Evil, Evil, as we do Fire, Fire, in its own name, when we would get it quenched) which men call Lechery in any, but an unclean Curioſity, that is, A deſire of knowing what is hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, to wit, the pleaſures, the ſecrets of another; and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedling with thoſe parts which nature and ſhame have retired, and ſhould be fore ever kept accordingly, but that the deſperately buſie iniquity of mans heart, can leave nothing free from the contamination of it ſelf with it? And what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is there then to have this Diſcipline of our Schools ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perviſed, that our Correctors, and their Rules, may be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42002:25"/>That our Teachers may be taught to be better. Away with ſuch doings from among us, which are ſo vile and brutiſh! Let the Horſes be ſlaſhed with a Whip to be learned to draw; Let the Dogs be beaten with your Cudgel, to teach them to crouch, or lie down: But let Children be inſtructed in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their Books, by thoſe means as are ſuteable to Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures endued with underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and thoſe Seeds of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as are ſprouting out, and ought to be ſuckled with a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der cultivation. It is a prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous courſe doubtleſs, that Children ſhould be, as it were, ſuppoſed all born mad, and ſo ſent to School onely as to <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam,</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:42002:25"/>to be made ſober by cruel handling; <hi>Minimum ſanè libê<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, iſtum decet, cui tantum licet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the training up of Children to virtue and good literature; it is beyond doubt a noble thing in its own nature, and might be an imployment of grandeur, for the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly born and qualified, the moſt generous minds, and braveſt ſpirits; and none elſe ſhould be admitted to ſo excellent a ſervice for the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> were it not for theſe barbarous cuſtoms, as being received of ſome degenerate Nations (in ſo filly methods of teaching, and this ſordid way of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) have diſhonoured that Profeſſion, and rendred the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:42002:26"/>School-maſter by ſo filthy a practiſe (unto which yet uſe doth ordinarily reconcile him) an office no more hallowed, then that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Lictor, or Beadle in other Nations. Not but there have been ſome Maſters of that ingenuity and modeſty, as they could never once find in their hearts to uſe this ſort of puniſhment to any that ever they brought up; Nor but there are ſome others who have taken up the common u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage without reflexion, and their hearts cannot reproach them, that they have ever exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed it from any inſtigation whereof they ſhould be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but onely out of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs for their Scholars ſake
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:42002:26"/>altogether, in the amendment of their manners, or quickning them in their Books. Theſe are ſuch, <hi>cujus praecordia ex me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liore luto finxit Titan,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently ſuch, as we have too much reaſon and experience to convince us, they are not the moſt. We dare not condemn a whole Generation of men that have uſed this practiſe, but we muſt condemn the practice, becauſe if all be not, ſo many are, abuſed with it. And in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that young men ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who are in the heat of their blood, as of their parts (which if it were not for this dark al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, and the effects of it, were for the fleſhing them in the Greek and Latin a few
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42002:27"/>years, a thing moſt adviſeable) are received to the office; We cannot but believe it a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous permiſſion, which brings mens corruption, and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo unheedfully together; knowing too ſenſibly, how ſome perſons corruption leads them into temptation, and ſome perſons temptation into cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Ita ingenium eſt omnium</l>
               <l>Hominum, a labore proclive ad libidinem.</l>
            </q>
            <p>It is indeed but a folly and preſumption for men to take on them an office, which they have not ability to manage. That imployment will be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, thoſe men uneaſie.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42002:27"/>There are ſeveral abilities muſt go to make a man a perfect fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to breed up Scholars; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the which, theſe two are the chiefeſt, a temperate Mind, and unwearied Diligence. That perſon, who by ſweetneſs and gentleneſs, or by the gravity of his deportment and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; or elſe by prudence and contrivance, is not able to awe and keep a company of Youth in obedience, without violence and ſtripes, ſhould judge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf no more fit for that Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then if he had no skill in the Latin and Greek; and ſuch ſhould never be admitted to this charge, by thoſe who have the nomination or election. For when we would have it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42002:28"/>look'd upon as a dignity (which was now ſaid) or a matter of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, (as really it is) like the being ſent into a Province, for a man to be eſteemed ſo pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, ſo vertuous, ſo worthy as to be choſen Praefect of the Children of a Town, in his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance into a publick School, and made Ruler over a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, over fifties, and over tens; We cannot but deſire, that thing may be ſuffered no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, which does bring it in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour; And that, as there may be an Inſcription now ſet up to that Perſon (like to the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Rome</hi>) who hath but diſcharged this Office vertuouſly; ſo may it be as rare a thing for the future, to find
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42002:28"/>any that do otherwiſe, or whoſe Acts are ever any more unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming ingenuity and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>Our Schools, we know in the Latin, are called <hi>Ludi, Ludi Literarii,</hi> and our Maſters, <hi>Ludi Magiſtri.</hi> From hence we may take the indication, that the erudition of Children, among the wiſer Antients, was thought beſt to be carried on in the way of Sport and Exerciſe. As the young men went to their Games to get the Garland in the exerciſe of their ſtrength, the <hi>Children</hi> were to go to their Books to exerciſe their wits. There would be no need of the Parents ſollicitude, or the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſtr pes, to bring the Child
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42002:29"/>to his learning; if the Methods of it were caſt into that mould, as ſhould make all their <hi>Leſſons</hi> appear only as ſo many Playes and Recreations, from which they ſhould be kept oftentimes as by the reines, to raiſe their minds into more earneſtneſs, rather then be ſpurred, as we are commonly, and galled only to the ſame. Let the Boys be ſet a running, as it were, with one another, in getting without Book; Let them be ſet a wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, in Conſtruing and Parſing; Let them in the whole buſineſs of the School, be chearfully ſtriving with themſelves and fellows in underſtanding, who ſhall excel, and wear the Wreath of their Maſters commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:42002:29"/>If any Boy ſhall be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, or do unworthily, le him be turned out of the <hi>School</hi> to Trap in the Fields, or to Nine-pins in the Streets, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe rude and illiterate Boyes who are no Scholars; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made to account ſo heavily of that, as to know his total excluſion, were indeed the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treameſt puniſhment. But if any are diligent, and deſerve encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, let them not only be admitted to higher degrees of exerciſe, but to ſome more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate converſe of their Maſter in reading of Hiſtory, or other delightful ſtudies; which he ſhould ſo illuſtrate and apply, as may both tend to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs in knowledge, and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42002:30"/>their ſpirits to honour &amp; virtue. It is not the Boys warm Bed, or Breakfaſt, not the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries of his Meat &amp; Drink, no not his Balls and Bounding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones, his Top and his Bandy, would be ſo delicious to him, as the time he was thus ſuffered to be with his Maſter, if our <hi>Schools</hi> were but ſo order'd, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where they ſhould be, that the matters there performed, were made to become in effect onely the Boys Olympicks, or ſo many Games of the Muſes, unto which they had recourſe for their delight and glory.</p>
            <p>Not that when we write this, it may be ever expected any thing in this World ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately be perfect. There
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:42002:30"/>will be ſome Maſters, and ſome Boys bad enough; and there may be ſome faults, which not only deſerve, but are fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive exemplary Correction. Let that chaſtiſement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, which is tolerated in our Schools, have an ingenuous ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration. Let no Child at any time be puniſhed in the Maſters heat or paſſion; If it be a fault now, it will be ſo an hour hence; if it appear not a crime to morrow, it was not ſo hainous as he thought it to be yeſterday. Let the Boy then undergoe a ſolemn kind of Judicature; If it were by a form of the ſame Boys as Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors together with their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:42002:31"/>it were but like the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonian</hi> Inſtitution of their Youth, whereof the chief point lay in this, To enable them to judge aright of the Good and Evil, or of what was praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, and what to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, in humane Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Whatſoever the Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal can alleadge for himſelf, by way of juſtification, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuation of his Fact, it ought to be heard both with patience and candour. If his Fault may be forgiven, without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to the reſt by the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, it were beſt: If not, Let the Doublet be plucked off, and that part which may chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lie naked, be ſtripped; Let
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:42002:31"/>the number of ſtripes, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the merits of his delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency, be allotted, and the Boy brought before the face of his Maſter for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſt execution. This is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Judgement, The Malefactour was to lie down before the Judge, and ſo receive the ſtripes he appointed. Let one of the vileſt Boys then, he that hath behaved himſelf worſt of any that day in the School, be picked out for Executioner; which may ſerve for a ſhame and admonition to him, as for his fellows ſuffering. If the Maſter will do it himſelf, it ſhall be reckoned only to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his virtue; for ſo long
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:42002:32"/>as he may not lay his ſtripes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more on thoſe parts which ſtir his original corruption, and he ſtayes ſtill the paſſing of Judgment, till he is calm in the point of Indignation, there will be no fear any farther of thoſe extremities which have been uſed: But we ſhould ſee how cool theſe men would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to the Work for hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, unto which they are to be led only by Righteouſneſs, and not by affection. For if there be not now twenty and twenty faults of ours obſerved or made by them, to bring us under their unclean ſtripes, unto one, that they would judge then worthy of their juſt ſeverity in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:42002:32"/>a ſlow and chaſte puniſhment, we dare forfeit the benefit of this Petition.</p>
            <p>We muſt confeſs, we are perhaps too much engaged in our own Cauſe. We find not theſe lines flow from us, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther careleſly, nor very eaſily, but with ſollicitude and much reflexion. We know the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt is ſingular and momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous. The iſſue we know not. The Tempers, Judgments, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and Reſentments of People, are various; and many will make a matter of jeſt, the moſt but a talk, of that which others will lay to heart. The Lord Almighty, who knows the thoughts of all, and their
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:42002:33"/>Actions, and what is Good or Evil in the Earth; doth know what need there is of ſuch a Suite. We have many times had our apprehenſions filled with terror, our mouths with crying, and our eyes with tears for the preſent ſmart which hath vaniſhed; but the abiding evil upon ſuch Acts, (or many ſuch) when they are done, and the allowance of the ſame, does affect us with apprehenſions of another rank. It does afflict us really, that there ſhould be ſo much obliquity in humane nature, that is, that there ſhould be ſo much <hi>corruption</hi> as there is, <hi>in the World</hi> (according to Saint <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>through luſt.</hi> It
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:42002:33"/>afflicts us much more, that the ſeeds of the ſame corruption which is practiſed in the Earth, ſhould not be unſown in our own hearts. We are grieved at our very ſouls, that a thing ſo holy as the Diſcipline of Children, and the Correction of them ought to be, ſhould by any means be lyable to abuſe, and much more to be made a procurer to vice. We are grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved yet, that this evil more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, having a root more deep perhaps in the fleſh then is ſeen, and through the tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and uſe, appearing under the ſhew of Good, or palliated at leaſt ſo, as to remain undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned; it is ſo hard for any
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:42002:34"/>to come ever to a meet repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance about the ſame. And that which adds to this, is, That if ſome of our more ſagacious Friends become ſenſible of ſomewhat by our complaints, and ſo ſend for, or go to our Maſters to reprove what is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs; they are not able to call the thing by its name, but in modeſty ſpeaking a little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their over-rigour, or the like, they leave the beam un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched; and ſo the perſon, for want of plainer rebuke, is but the rather hardned by it; Which, if the living in the leaſt ſin with full conſent of will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, be a matter ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous as all hold, muſt be of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:42002:34"/>a conſequence no leſs then damnable to them, who make it ſo deplorable to us.</p>
            <p>Theſe premiſes therefore conſidered, we cannot but make our appeal, in this ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Century, and ſeventieth approaching Year of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World, (ſeeing it hath not been done before) to the Heads of our Nation now Aſſembled, and to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> againſt this <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaenum triſte</hi> (if we may uſe <hi>Juvenals</hi> expreſſion) which hath been mentioned. That is, We humbly implore the Higher Powers, that this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure practice, which hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in our Schools hitherto, without controul or detection,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:42002:35"/>(unleſs what hath been private only) may come under pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick cenſure, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prohibition, and extermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as a thing, if examined in the ſource and effects of it, not only what all know it, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum triſte,</hi> but <hi>Malum turpe,</hi> and an iniquity to be puniſhed by the Judges. <hi>Et fecit Aſa quod rectum videbatur in oculis Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vae, nam abſtulit moritorios è ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, &amp; amovit Deos ſtercoreos quos fecerant majores ſui.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42002:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
